A Guide to the Tracy W. McGregor Autograph Collection, ca. 1599-1947
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- SERIES I. LETTERS & MANUSCRIPTS
  - Joseph Conrad to Edward Garnett [1896 Apr 13], AL, 2p. (Box 2)
    Sends 24 pages of a manuscript for him to see, "Is the thing tolerable? Is the thing readable? Is the damned thing altogether insupportable? Am I mindful enough of your teaching - of your expounding of the ways of the readers?" and admits he is ready to "cut, slash, erase, destroy; spit, trample, jump, wipe my feet on that ms at a word from you"; #38-732
  - Joseph Conrad to Edward Garnett [1896 Nov 25], ALS, 1p. (Box 2)
    Pleased with what S.S. Pawling writes, thanks Garnett for arranging the publication of The Nigger of the Narcissus and expresses his fears over composing the ending of the book; #38-732
  - Joseph Conrad to Edward Garnett 1897 May 26, ALS, 4p. (Box 2)
    Thanks Garnett for his letter about The Nigger of the Narcissus, mentions a visit from S.S. Pawling, and anticipates reading Marius the Epicurean; #38-732
  - Joseph Conrad to Edward Garnett [1897 Aug 24], ALS, 4p. (Box 2)
    Sends a short preface to The Nigger of the Narcissus and asks if it cannot be printed but leaves it to Garnett's discretion; the Preface appeared in The New Review but was suppressed when the novel was published in book form; #38-732
  - Joseph Conrad to Edward Garnett 1897 Aug 28, ALS, 6p. (Box 2)
    Incorporates the changes suggested by Garnett in the Preface to The Nigger of the Narcissus, discusses a letter received from William Blackwood saying Karain will be published in November and asking if he had any long story which could be published as a serial in his magazine, and attributes all good moments in his literary life to Garnett; #38-732
  - Joseph Conrad to Edward Garnett 1897 Dec 23, ALS, 4p.; With envelope (Box 2)
    Waits anxiously for the William Morris book; and discusses reviews of The Nigger of the Narcissus, especially the enthusiasm of Quiller-Couch in his review in Pall Mall Magazine who says the book must be a success; also is writing The Rescue, "I am harassed with anxieties but the thing comes out!"; #38-732
  - Joseph Conrad to Edward Garnett 1898 Aug 3, ALS, 4p.; with envelope (Box 2)
    Expresses discouragement at his literary impasse regarding The Rescue, "I am not dead tho only half alive. Very soon I shall send you some ms. I am writing hopelessly - but still I am writing. How I feel I cannot express. Pages accumulate and the story stands still. I feel suicidal.... I am afraid there's something wrong with my thinking apparatus. I am utterly out of touch with my work - and I can't get in touch. All is darkness.; #38-732
  - Joseph Conrad to Edward Garnett 1899 Nov 13, ALS, 2p. (Box 2)
    Expresses delight that Garnett's first book of criticism will soon appear but urges that dubious personalities (like himself) be excluded, even if deserving, as to give no opportunity for others to question his judgment about literature; will send a book by Robert Bridges; and says that his question about The Rescue sends shivers along his back' #38-732
  - Joseph Conrad to Edward Garnett 1912 Oct 16, ALS, 2p. (Box 2)
    Speaks warmly of Garnett's custom of sending Conrad criticisms of his books but asks him not to let them interfere with his own work, suffers an attack of gout, and discusses Richard Curle's review of Twixt Land and Sea, "That criticism is something and no mistake. All that went before seems mere verbiage in comparison. I am exceedingly pleased. Give him my friendly greeting."; #38-732
  - Joseph Conrad to Edward Garnett 1920 Jul 11, ALS, 2p.; with envelope (Box 2)
    Trouble with his wrist has been disabling at times, has heeded all of Garnett's advice and recommendations concerning The Rescue, and discusses the criticism of his character Mrs. Travers, Lingard, and the Emma, admitting that "being afraid of striking a false note I failed to do her justice - not so much in action, I think, as in expression"; #38-732
  - Joseph Conrad to Edward Garnett 1920 Nov 8, ALS, 2p.; with envelope (Box 2)
    Gives advice to Garnett about writing a novel, "But before everything switch off the critical current of your mind and work in darkness - the creative darkness which no ghost of responsibility will haunt"; #38-732
  - Joseph Conrad to Edward Garnett 1923 Aug, ALS, 2p.; with envelope (Box 2)
    Refers to his indebtedness to Garnett for all of his help and assistance in the past in molding his literary work from the very beginning of his career, "Straight from the sea into your arms, as it were. How much you have done to pull me together intellectually only the Gods that brought us together know. For I myself don't. All I had in my hand was some little creative gift - but not even one single piece of 'cultural' baggage."; #38-732
  - Joseph Conrad to Arthur Symons 1909-1921, 15 ALS (Box 2)
    Conrad discusses his health (1909 Jun 24; 1910 May 6; [1913 Apr 22] & [1913 Aug 2]; 1915 Oct 28; 1921 Sep 12; and n.d. Saturday evening); sends thanks for gifts sent to him (1910 Dec 24; 1914 Jan 7; 1916 Dec 9); urges Symons to rid himself of all his uneasiness ([1911 May 11]); appreciates his praise for his work (1912 Jan 25); experiences car trouble ([1913 Apr 22]); bemoans the bad behavior of publishers (1915 Oct 28; 1921 Sep 12); praises Symons prose and poetry (1918 Dec 9; n.d. Saturday evening); mentions his son at home after being gassed during the war (1918 Dec 9)] formerly in McGregor slipcase 46; #38-732
  - Joseph Conrad to "Dear Sir" 1896 Sep 24, ALS, 2p. (Box 2)
    Thanks him for his letter and his skill in negotiating for the "happy termination of that Cosmopolitan episode," glad that [Ortman?] is a sensible man, and tells him that his next short story will be ready in ten days; #38-732-a
  - Charles Cornwallis to his chief of staff, Lt. Colonel Nisbet Balfour 1780 Nov 21, ALS, 2p., fragment (Box 2)
    Concerning logistics and the movements of Lt. Colonel Tarleton, written from Waynesborough, South Carolina, prior to the invasion of North Carolina by Cornwallis in his march to Virginia, fragment with signature missing; #2517
  - "Memorial in Relation to Carolina" by Dr. [Daniel] Coxe [ca. 1720], AD, 11p. (Box 2)
    Begins with a recitation of the original grant made by Charles I in 1630, to Sir Robert Heath and his heirs, of all that Province of Carolina lying on the Gulf of Mexico and the Atlantic Ocean, listing all those with title to the land up to Dr. Coxe. After proving his title to the property, Coxe then describes his efforts at settling the Province; #1178
  - Varina Anne Jefferson Davis to General Bradley Tyler Johnson 1885 Mar 13, ALS, 4p. (Box 2)
    Thanks him for his gift of the Army of Northern Virginia badge of the "Old Maryland Line," which he sent to her father, Jefferson Davis, discusses her father's illness, and expresses regret at missing his visit; #10547-ai
  - William Menzies to Charles Deane, with a postal card from Charles Deane and printed item 1881 May 27, ALS, 1p. (Box 2)
    Related to the The First Plymouth Patent purchased by the noted New York Americana book collector William Menzies, sometime after 1866. The First Plymouth Patent, originally granted on June 1, 1621, was the first book printed on vellum in the United States. The volume was edited by Charles Deane, member of the Massachusetts Historical Society, and privately printed from the manuscript in 1854; #10547-u
  - Richard B. Shepard to Frederick Dellenbaugh 1926 Apr 22, ALS, 1p. (Box 2)
    Believes his review of James Bridger is satisfactory and asks Dellenbaugh to autograph all of his books for Shepard's private library; #10547-aj
  - J. Cecil Alter to Frederick Dellenbaugh 1933 Feb 15, TLS, 1p., with envelope (Box 2)
    Thanks him for clippings concerning the "Naming of Arizona and the Painted Desert" and asks for a copy of "The Naming of the Grand Canyon," and tells him he has a set of the Colorado River Hearings on his shelf and a full set of Dellenbaugh's books; #10547-aj
  - William DeMorgan to Mr. Ellis 1912 Dec 20, ALS, 3p. (Box 2)
    Discusses his recollections of his old neighborhood at 40 Fitzroy Square and some of the houses there, including that of Abraham Ward, a copper engraving, and James Ward's house, which he "transcribed into Alice-for-Short; #10547-ak
  - Thomas DeQuincey to "My dear Sir" [James Augustus Hessey?] 1821 Dec 27, ALS, 2p. (Box 2)
    Writes concerning his illness, difficulties of arranging for a man to come and pack his books, and arrangements for his travel from London; #10547-al
  - Portrait of Thomas DeQuincey by Jacques Reich n.d. (Box 2)
    #10547-al
  - Charles Dickens to Henry Stevens 1866 Feb 27, ALS, 1p., with envelope (Box 2)
    Regrets that he was to unwell to come to the Athenaeum and vote for Stevens and assures him that the loss will be only a "temporary vexation"; #10547-dn
  - Henry F. Dickens to Whitelaw Saunders 1919 Jun 10, ALS, 4p. (Box 2)
    Encloses a check signed by his father Charles Dickens, and relates an incident at a Christmas party in 1869 where Dickens recalled the address "Warren's Blacking, 30 Strand," where he had worked as a child, while playing The Memory Game; the family did not learn that he had incorporated his childhood experiences into his novel David Copperfield until after his death; #10547-am
  - Emily Dickinson to [Mrs.] Annie [P. Strong] [ca. 1882], ALS, 1p. (Box 2)
    Comments that Delawares were the favorite grapes of her mother and asks Mrs. Strong to set the bit of cake in the garden so the robins can have a taste; #10547-an
  - Bibliographical Notes in Dutch concerning Adriaen van der Donck's book on the New Netherlands n.d., AMs, 2p. (Box 2)
    #10547-ao
  - Norman Douglas to Mr. Harris 1925 Nov 7, ALS, 1p. (Box 2)
    Writes concerning the printing of his Capri things; #10547-ap
  - Norman Douglas to "Dear Sir" 1926 May 21, TLS, 1p. (Box 2)
    Offers to sell his manuscript of Fountains in the Sand which was bound in two unequal volumes and has a bibliographical value because it differs from the printed version, "There is a story, a kind of novel, running through it, which I subsequently extirpated at the advice - I wish now I had not taken it - of my friend Joseph Conrad"; #10547-ap
  - Norman Douglas to Colonel Palmer n.d., ANS, 1p. (Box 2)
    Writes he cannot come due to his sprained ankle; #10547-ap
  - Arthur Conan Doyle to Herbert Greenough Smith 1898-1929, 22 ALS (Box 2)
    About the following topics: "The Story of the Clubfooted Grocer" and "The Story of the Black Doctor" ([1898]); his stories about Brigadier Gerard ([1902]; [several in 1903]; ); "The Leather Funnel" ([1903]);"Sir Nigel" (1905 Nov 14 & 27; [1905]; [ca. 1905 Dec]; [post 1905]); "The White Prophet" (1909 Jun 4); "The Gibraltar Tunnel" (1914 Mar 23); and "The Lord of the Dark Face" ([1929]; #10547-d
  - Arthur Conan Doyle to Herbert Greenough Smith n.d., 36 ALS (Box 2)
    About the following topics: spiritualism and the supernatural; the legal case of George Edalji (occupying his interest in 1907); "The Machine Article" appearing in The Strand; "A Shadow Before"; the Bristol Reform Riots; another writer's criminal biography "The Episodes of Marge"; child studies; Birdie Edwards; and Madeleine Smith. Topics mentioned here have been placed within the folder in separate inserts; #10547-d
  - Arthur Conan Doyle to Herbert Greenough Smith ca. 1915-1919, 33 ALS (Box 2)
    Re The British Campaign in France, chiefly the letters discuss the publication of his history of the British involvement in World War I in The Strand Magazine, including a typed letter from R.W. Brade about censorship (1915 May 14) but they also include the following subjects: his "Child Studies" (n.y. Nov 2); and an undated reference to Sherlock Holmes "RIP"; #10547-d
  - Arthur Conan Doyle to Herbert Greenough Smith ca. 1901-1917, 13 ALS (Box 2)
    Re Sherlock Holmes, including "The Adventure of Black Peter" ([1904]); and "The Adventure of the Dancing Men" ([ca. 1904]; #10547-d
  - Draft of the Introduction and Notes for The Witchcraft Delusion in New England, edited by Samuel Gardner Drake; #10547- aq ca. 1866, AMs, 46p. (Box 2)
  - Drafts of a Preface, Memoir of Robert Calef, Notes re More Wonders of the Invisible World, Pedigree of Calef and Index by editor, Samuel G. Drake; #10547-aq ca. 1866, AMs (Box 2)
  - Copy of a Proclamation by John Murray, Earl of Dunmore, regarding a border dispute between Pennsylvania and Virginia; #1668 1774 Sep 17, AD, 1p. (Box 3)
  - Copy of a Proclamation by John Murray, Earl of Dunmore, regarding a border dispute between Pennsylvania and Virginia 1774 Sep 17, AD, 2p. (Box 3)
    #2839
  - Charles Baxter to James Nicol Dunn 1889-1904, 6 ALS (Box 3)
    Concerning research and publications about Robert Louis Stevenson; #38-730
  - Letters to James Nicol Dunn, from Walter Biggar Blaikie, Sidney Colvin, William Ernest Henley, and [David Watson] Stevenson ca. 1890-1911, 9 ALS (Box 3)
    Topics include Robert Louis Stevenson, The Irony of Nature by P. Anderson Graham, and Rudyard Kipling; #10547-e
  - Letters to George Eliot 1865-1878, 12 ALS (Box 3)
    Correspondents include: John Emerich Edward Dalberg Acton, discussing Eliot's literary style; Richard Monckton Milnes Houghton; Benjamin Jowett, discussing the "antiquated philosophies of Germany"; Leslie Stephen, answers her question concerning scholarships at Cambridge University; David Masson, thanks her for her comments about his book on John Milton; John, Vicount Morley, asking her to write concerning William Shakespeare; Frederic William Henry Myers, concerning their travel plans and the drowning of the Furney sisters in the Nile; James Thomson discussing his poem, The City of Dreadful Night and his attitude towards life, comparing it to the Italian poet, Giacomo Leopardi; and Anthony Trollope, sending a copy of Rachel Ray and admitting that he wrote about "commonplace life among the most ordinary people" unlike Eliot; #10547-f
  - Letters from Ralph Waldo Emerson 1848-1861, 3 ALS (Box 3)
    Emerson writes to an unidentified correspondent to introduce two of his acquaintances who wish to meet an Oxford fellow while touring England and that he has seen Alfred Tennyson (1848); he writes to William Webb Follett Synge concerning John Hiram Lathrop (1852); and asks Henry Oscar Houghton to print a thousand copies of Conduct of Life for Ticknor & Fields (1861); #10547-ar
  - Legal Papers of the Eskridge-Gerard families 1653-1753, 30 ADS (Box 3)
    Concerning property in Westmoreland County and Northumberland County, including indentures, deeds, bonds, patents, judgment in settling Gerard estate, copy of John Gerard's will, powers of attorney, and bill of sale for slaves (1738); signed by Anne Allerton, Richard Bennett, William Berkeley, Landon Carter, Richard Coles, George Conway, Jane Eskridge, Robert Eskridge, John Gerard, Thomas Gerard, Mary Hawkins, William Hockaday, Daniel Hornbye, Richard Jackson, William R. Jackson, Elizabeth Johnson, W. Jordan, George Lee, Richard Lee, John Llewellin, Henry Miller, Willoughby Newton, Thomas Pope, Peter Rust, William Tebbs, and Peter Temple; #3009
  - Letters from William Hockaday to Thomas Gerard 1659-1666, 6 ALS (Box 3)
    Concerning the property of the Eskridge-Gerard families of Westmoreland County and Northumberland County; #3009
  - Eskridge-Gerard Papers 1667-1668, 14 ADS (Box 3)
    Regarding a suit between George Ludlow and Thomas Gerard concerning land in Westmoreland County; #3009
  - 1738-1744, 6ADS (Box 3)
    Legal documents from the Eskridge-Gerard families of Westmoreland County and Northumberland County, including indentures, bonds, deeds, etc.; #3009
  - Edward Everett to A.H.H. Stuart 1859 Apr 9, ALS, 2p., with envelope (Box 3)
    Offers to visit Staunton on the 25th to give the promised speech; #2941
  - Edward Everett to Professor Parker Cleaveland (1780-1858) 1820 Apr 29, ALS, 2p. (Box 3)
    Passes on the request of The North American Review for Cleaveland to do an article or review of any work concerning American geology for the July number; #4650
  - Legal Papers of the Fairfax Family and Lee Family 1753-1808, 51 ADS (Box 3)
    Includes bonds, agreements, complaints, depositions, indentures, lease, power of attorney, and promissory notes, pertaining to Denny Fairfax, Ferdinando Fairfax, George William Fairfax, Louisa Fairfax, Thomas Fairfax, Catherine Lee, Charles Lee, Flora Lee, Francis Lightfoot Lee, Henry Lee, James Lee, Lancelot Lee, Mary Lee, Mathilda Lee, Philip Lee, Philip Ludwell Lee, Richard Bland Lee, Richard Henry Lee, Thedorick Lee, and Thomas Ludwell Lee, as well as other families; #1106-a
  - Two Fairfax Family and Lee Family Indentures 1792 & 1796 (Box 3)
    #1106-a
  - Francis Fauquier to Richard Bland 1760 Jul 28, ALS, 2p. (Box 3)
    Assures Bland that his contribution to the relief of Boston will be published correctly, comments on the affair of the Rev. Jacob Rowe at William and Mary, and thanks Bland for a copy of his pamphlet defending the state of Virginia's actions in the matter of clerical salaries; #10127-a
  - Abstract of land patent from Cecil Calvert Lord Baltimore to Josias Fendall of lands on the west side of Patuxent River, called Cold Spring Manor 1658 Sep 25, AD, 1p. (Box 3)
    #10547-as
  - Typescript of a manuscript journal by Robert H. Fisher, of Suffolk, entitled Narrative of a Voyage to the West Indies, for the purpose of attempting the establishment of an ice market in the Island of Jamaica1800-1801, TMs (Box 3)
    #3863
  - John Fiske to Mlle. Veltin, with unrelated fragment of manuscript regarding Some Years of Travel1898 May 20, ALS, 1p. (Box 3)
    #38-650
  - An untitled Christmas carol by Edward Fitzgerald, beginning "Sing, ye children, songs of gladness" n.d., AMs, 3p., with a typescript copy (Box 3)
    #38-371-a
  - Edward Fitzgerald to Miss Anna Beddill 1876 Aug 8, ALS, 8p. (Box 3)
    Mentions the work of Thomas Babington Macaulay which he likes although he does not have faith enough to read history; is reading Captain Burton's Iceland; mentions Sir Walter Scott and The Pirate, Bernard Quaritch, who is reprinting his version of a Greek play, which contains an absurd blunder, Thomas Carlyle, and William Kemble; #38-731-a
  - Edward Fitzgerald to the Reverend George Crabbe [1849 Nov 20], ALS, 1p. (Box 3)
    Discusses his visit to the "great Scotchman" Thomas Carlyle, and Crabbe's opinion of Carlyle; and urges Crabbe to read his book Past and Present; #38-731-a
  - Correspondence of Dorothy Furman and Louis H. Gray 1899, 3 ALS & clipping (Box 3)
    Re: Furman's Bibliography of Edward Fitzgerald, with a copy of the news clipping containing the bibliography in The New York Times Saturday Review, June 10, 1899; #38-731-a
  - Account Sales of the Estate of William Flood, Westmoreland County, Virginia, including slaves 1775 (Box 3)
    #3620
  - West Florida Land Documents, addressed to or signed by Governor Peter Chester, including three warrants of survey (one with attached plat) for land in West Florida, and two petitions to waive costs of surveying land 1772-1778, 6 ADS (Box 3)
    #10547-at
  - Scribes' copies of Correspondence of Vicente Folch, Governor of West Florida, and Juan Ventura Morales, Intendant of West Florida 1810, 63 items (Box 3)
    Concerning the affairs of West Florida in the months before President James Madison's proclamation took control of this territory for the United States; #6665
  - Copy of original Survey of Land, 1769 Aug 3, in East Florida by the Surveyor General William Gerrard de Brahm ordered by James Grant 1823, In a burgundy slipcase, located in oversize box X-1 (Box 3)
    #4500
  - 1794-1820, 29 ALS (Box 4)
    Letters to Ebenezer Foote, a Federalist of New York State, from Loring Andrews, John Avery, Samuel Augustus Barker; C.E. Edmunds, Charles A. Foote, John Foote (to Frederick Foote), Justin Foote, Barent Gardenier, Daniel Hale, Jacob Morris; John Radcliff, Stephen van Rensselaer, William Root, Henry van Schaack, William Thompson, Abraham van Vechten, and A.D. Zeng, concerning national politics and the villainy of the Jeffersonian party, especially: Elbridge Gerry and the XYZ Affair (1798 Oct 11); Jefferson and the Presidential election of 1800 (1800 May 30); the bitterness between the "Clintonians and the Lewisites," contemporary political factions (1806 Apr 7); George Clinton, the Embargo, and Thomas Jefferson (1808 Jan 8); James Madison and the Embargo (1808 Jan 14); John Adams being suspect as a true Federalist (1808 Jan 22); controversies surrounding the presidential election of 1808 (most of the letters of that year); George Clinton (1808 Aug 8); the character of Thomas Jefferson (1808 Apr 7; Aug 10); the Embargo (Aug 10 & 25; Oct 28); references to the opinion of Edmond Charles Genet concerning Thomas Jefferson, James Madison, and Napoleon (Hale - 1808 Aug 10); James Madison (1808 Nov 8); Other topics include: business (1794 Nov; 1808 Mar 30); Napoleon Bonaparte and his activities (1808 Jan 29; Mar 10; Aug 22); the National Bank (1811 Sep 2); and slavery (1820 Apr 29); #4887
  - An unpublished essay by the Reverend Thomas Foxcroft, Minister of the First Church, Boston, Massachusetts, entitled An Essay to Explain some Articles in the Platform for the reducing unto Practice, the third way of communion: in the manner stated by the Synod 1662; to wit by The consociation of churches in a vicinity. By a Friend to Congregational principles. Proposed as meet to be considered by the churches at the present juncture by reason of the late difficulties & proceedings at Salem[1735], AMs, 47p. (Box 4)
    #38-362
  - The Reverend Benjamin Colman to the Reverend Thomas Foxcroft, accompanying the above essay by Foxcroft and stating that Coleman has read the essay, and is returning it along with his various suggestions 1735 Nov 17, ALS, 3p. (Box 4)
  - Captain Edward Foy to Edward Hand, Royal Irish Regiment of Foot at Philadelphia 1774 Mar 2, ALS, 2p. (Box 4)
    Writes concerning Hand's land claims, that according to the Proclamation of 1763, Lord Dunmore does not grant lands to anyone not a military officer and that the warrants of survey specify that they are to locate only where no prior grants have been made or any settlement actually appears; #2290
  - Petition of the Freeholders of Hull, Massachusetts, to the General Court, Boston, Massachusetts, concerning use of land and fishing rights, including a resolution with justifications for the rejection of the petition on the verso; signed by Nathaniel Gossworth, Thomas Colier, Richard Russell, Edward Johnson, and Joseph Hills 1663 May 27 (Box 4)
    #10547-bk
  - James Anthony Froude to "My dearest Fanny" n.y. Feb 19, ALS, 4p. on 1 l. (Box 4)
    Discusses John Bunyan, evangelicalism, the Oxford Movement, and Arthur Hugh Clough; #10547-au
  - Autobiography of Henry Fry describing his conversion to Methodism n.d., AMs, 24p. (Box 4)
    #2848
  - Letters from John Galsworthy to H. Newell-Smith, Eric Sewell-Alger, Sir J. Simpson, and unknown correspondents 1910-1928, 6 ALS (Box 4)
    Discusses The Spirit of Punishment circulated by the Humanitarian Society and Penal Reform League; Joseph Conrad and his books, The Secret Agent and Tales of Hearsay; gives literary advice; and mentions his latest book just published and Villa Rubein; #10547-g
  - Royal Patent granted to Bernardo de Galvez by Charles III of Spain, containing an official account of his achievement in Louisiana during the struggle between Spain and Great Britain for domination in the Southeastern region of present day United States. 1783 May 20, AD, 35p. (Box 4)